Welcome, everybody. I'm
Dr. Patricia Koyman, and
we will be having a
lecture today on the Upper
Crossed Syndrome and
Postural Considerations.
Here are the session
objectives. These are
also outlined in your
class preparation guide.
Number one, we're first
going to review a historical
background or perspective
from Hippocrates to A
.T. Still to consideration
of the five or six
osteopathic models to Dr.
Phil Greenman's legacy and on
to the related interprofessional
and global awareness
of the upper and lower
crossed syndrome from
the legacy of neurologists,
Drs. Yanda and Lewitt.
Second, you'll be able
to understand in this
lecture the upper crossed
syndrome, including the
role of type 1 slow twitch
postural and type 2 fast
twitch phasic muscles. The
students will understand
which muscles need
stretching and which
muscles need strengthening
in relation to application
of an understanding of
this crossed syndrome.
Specific exercises will
be reviewed at the end of
the lecture with pictures
and diagrams included.
Thirdly, the students will
be able to understand the
importance of obtaining
and considering a patient's
history, subjective, along
with objective information.
This objective information
can include special tests,
muscle testing and palpation,
the osteopathic structural
examination, postural
observation and analysis, other
neurological nerve conduction
velocity or electromyography
or radiological x-rays
mri etc testing as needed
fourth students will be
able to understand how to
incorporate an understanding
of postural compensation
tensegrity also known as
biotensegrity gravitational strain
pathophysiology gsp and
postural decompensation into
their osteopathic perspective
and lastly students will
read the assigned article
from page. The link is here.
This is also listed in your
class preparation guide
and you'll read that
on your own and you
will get that will
help you to gain a
sense of a clinical
correlation or a clinical
suggestion related
to this topic area.
Brief outline,
historical perspective,
review muscle
types one and two,
upper cross syndrome,
postural considerations,
postural compensation,
tensegrity,
gravitational strain
pathophysiology, and postural
decompensation, and general
treatment strategies.
Okay, a historical
perspective. So nearly 2
,500 years ago, Hippocrates
said, the regimen
I adopt will be for the
benefit of my patients
according to my
abilities and judgment.
As we learn about postural
considerations in osteopathic
diagnosis and treatment,
we can consider principles
intended to enhance the
ability to understand postural
mechanisms as a dynamic
process or processes affecting
interrelated patient
neuromusculoskeletal function.
Also, you can consider
that with understanding
and practice, the
physician's judgment
in prescribing
individualized postural
treatment regimens will
evolve and improve.
According to Andrew Taylor
Still, an osteopath is only
a human engineer who should
understand all of the
laws governing his engine
and thereby master disease.
Andrew Taylor still placed
much emphasis on the
fascia and its relationship
to health. He wrote, I
know of no other part of
the body that equals the
fascia as a hunting ground
for health and disease.
By its action we live and
by its failure, we die.
Continuing with the
historical perspective,
here's a schematic
picture or drawing of the
original five models adopted
by the Educational Council
on Osteopathic Principles,
ECOP, back in 1982.
Here to the right, we
have a similar schematic
drawing an expanded six models
to include bioenergetics.
Here we have bioenergetics
in the middle with
the yellow sun image included
as well as additional
environmental stressors
that are cited around
the body mind spirit
encompassing circle here.
If you would like more
information on this expanded
six models. You can click
on this link here and
read about that in more
detail from chapter 61,
Dynamic Strain and
the Bioenergetics
Model in the current
fifth edition of the
Foundations of
Osteopathic Medicine.
So the historical
perspective includes the many
osteopathic approaches of
both diagnosis and treatment
that have evolved within
our profession over many,
many decades and still
evolving. Research is still
ongoing, and we are at
the tip of the iceberg
here. And in this lecture,
we'll be talking about
just one of the crossed
syndromes And within the
context that there are many
perspectives and approaches
that one can choose to
utilize in your evaluation
of your patient and your
decision to apply for
treatment for your patient,
one of the perspectives.
So we can think of DO,
Dr. Obastopathic
Medicine, as an acronym
for also DIG ON. That
means continue to search
and learn in your
osteopathic reasoning.
Over 100 years ago, even,
spreading the word
was Albert Hubbard.
And back in 1989, he
published a book after he
had visited the old doctor,
Andrew Taylor Still,
and published a 32-page
book which helped to spread
the word of osteopathy.
In our modern era, we
have other ways of
spreading the word with our
modern technologies, social
media, websites, etc.
And patients are finding
out about our osteopathic
perspective and approach
and looking for another way
to care for themselves, care
for their family, and find
healing from their
disorders, their pain, their
discomfort, whatever might be
going on. So as an osteopathic
physician or a student
physician becoming an
osteopathic physician in the
near future, keep this in
mind to always dig on,
continue to search and learn.
Here's a quote from A
.T. Still, osteopathy to
me is a very sacred
science. It is sacred
because it is a healing
power through all nature.
So, your digging on, your
search may bring you to
incorporate information and
or practical approaches which
originate from other fields
of reasoning, including,
but not limited to,
osteopathic medicine itself,
neurology, orthopedics,
physiatry, functional medicine,
or any other medical specialty
or primary care field,
bioenergetics, spirituality,
metabolism or slash
nutrition or any other
components of the six models of
osteopathic medicine which
we saw the schematic drawing
previously, chemistry,
physics, quantum physics,
biophysics or any other basic
pre-med or advanced level
sciences, embryology,
growth and development etc.
Any and all of these and
other fields not named
can inform your understanding
of the whole picture
for your patient and for
health and for healing.
Moving on to another
historical perspective,
Philip E. Greenman,
D-O-F-A-A-O, who lived
from 1928 to 2013, was also
digging on throughout his
osteopathic medical career.
Here's a picture, an image
of Greenman's works, the
collected works of Philip
Greenman, D-O-F-A-O, a
book published by the American
Academy of Osteopathy.
Here we have Dr. Greenman
himself. A quote from him,
what I do know is that
when I put my hands on a
patient as part of a comprehensive
physical examination.
I begin to evolve a
line of questioning that
isn't entirely conscious.
I pick up information in my
hands that guide the
questions I next need to ask.
And Dr. Greenman was a
professor at Michigan
State University College
of Osteopathic Medicine.
Now, Dr. Greenman was
also aware of the work of
Drs. Janda, Yanda, and
Lewitt and the crossed
syndromes. They were
approximately from the same era.
You can see Dr. Greenman
born in 1928 and passing
away in 2013, we see
in this picture here.
And this is in the green
highlight from his obituary
where they were talking about
some of the work that he
did sharing with the
profession, his manual medicine
approaches and teaching. He
did many courses and came up
with standard screening
approaches for patients, and
many people found this very
comprehensive and helpful
if you want to read through
the obituary reading here.
Again, Dr. Greenman
was a contemporary of
Dr. Vladimir Yanda.
Here we see that he
was also born in 1928,
passed away in 2002.
Dr. Yanda had a history
of poliomyelitis as a
teenager. He was
wheelchair bound for three
years after an initial
quadriplegia. He was a
neurologist trained at
Charles University in
Prague in the 1960s
in Canada. He did some
postdoctoral work with
Professor John Basmagian.
Sometimes Dr. Basmagian
wondered who was teaching
whom because Dr. Yanda
was very knowledgeable
himself in his postdoctoral
work. His work in
rehabilitation included
research and clinical activities
over many, many decades and
with a global influence.
He was editor-in-chief
of the Czech Journal of
Rehabilitation and Physical
Medicine until 2002.
He worked with Carl
Lewitt, MD, another Czech
neurologist, presenting
the upper and lower crossed
syndromes. So the upper and
lower cross syndromes come
from these two neurologists
from the Czech Republic,
Prague, from their work in
Charles University in Prague.
And Dr. Janda was also
known as the father of the
20th century rehabilitation
movement. And his
research and clinical
activities were related to
pediatrics, to geriatrics.
He also researched pediatric
conditions as the
patient became an adult,
neurodiagnostic testing,
postural neurologic disorders,
ankle conditions,
obscure ****** pain, etc.
So he had a breadth and
a depth of the research
that he was involved
with, and here is cited
the article where some
of this information
was obtained in the
picture here, which was
from a tribute to a
master of rehabilitation,
which you can see Dr.
Greenman, Dr. Phil Greenman
from Michigan State was
one of the co-authors
for that tribute as he
was aware of his work.
Here we can see a drawing
that Dr. Yanda had done,
one of his drawings
demonstrating postural
assessment. So he emphasized
the local and global
assessment as part of a
complete examination, teaching
methods that allowed the
examiner to quickly log
his or her findings. So
this is just one method.
And Dr. Yanda himself
would say to any
practitioner not to become
too stuck on your own
approach to your method
of recording or your
drawing or your system
to keep an open mind
to what you need to look
at for your patient.
in real time as well.
Okay, here's a schematic
diagram of what we're looking
for when we're treating our
patients. We want to find
a better balance, whether
we call that homeostasis or
homeodynamics, different
terminology that can lead
us to the same idea of
finding a balance. So if
we think about fitness
in terms of endurance,
mobility, and strength,
here we have like a seesaw
image of what's going on
with the muscles there
are postural muscles there
are phasic muscles and
how are these involved
in this crossed syndrome
so here we have a
question which muscles are
used and on the left
here we can see runners,
long distance runners,
or the Boston Marathon,
we can see this here,
and they're using the
type one tonic slow
twitch muscles for long
endurance work, postural
muscles, and these tend
to become facilitated
and shortened or tight.
And as a general category,
over here on the right,
we have the sprinters
or intermediate distance
runners using more of the
type two phasic fast twitch
muscles which fatigue more
easily and tend to become
inhibited and the muscles
can become weak sometimes
the word pseudoparetic
is used remember the
type one is for the endurance
long distance and have
a lower fatigue rate the
type two some of your
lectures may go into more
detail in terms of type 2a
which maybe have moderate
fatigue and they may have
moderate distances and
intensities when they're
used and type 2b which are
more for short distances
and high intensity and a high
or quick fatigue rate for
the 2b but we'll just keep
it as one category for this
lecture. Type 2, phasic,
becoming weak, and type 1,
postural, becoming more
shortened or tight.
You have some examples
of some runners,
short to intermediate
distance runners
here versus long
distance runners here.
Okay, so in clinical
practice, we distinguish
two muscle types in the
evaluation and treatment.
Type one, postural,
slow twitch.
Type two,
phasic, fast twitch.
So we'll review again
type one. These muscles
react by becoming
tight or shortened as
they become facilitated
in response to postural
imbalance, injury, or
somatic dysfunction.
So it is good to know
which muscles are being
categorized as postural,
slow twitch muscles.
Over here, again, the type
two, we're taking looking
at as a as a group okay these
muscles react by becoming
weak as they become inhibited
for instance the gluteus
medius muscle aphasic
muscle may become reflexly
inhibited due to an associated
sacroiliac issue for
example an extended sacrum a
torsion etc one side on one
side and thus causing the
muscle to become relatively
weak on that side versus
the other side the muscle
itself has not lost its
innate strength but rather is
inhibited and this becomes
weak as a result okay here
we have a table we're going
to focus on type one now
again postural slow twitch
becoming facilitated shortened
and tight so we're going
to focus first on this
for this lecture upper cross
syndrome here's an example
someone with a head forward
posture what's going on
the anterior muscles are
tight and shortened and
facilitated such as the pectoralis
muscles and the posterior
muscles are shortened
facilitated muscles can be
the levator scapula the upper
trapezius and the scm so
we have anterior and posterior
we'll look at pictures
soon okay and then now we
move on to type 2 phasic
fast twitch become inhibited
and thus weak we'll look
at upper cross syndrome
first example again the head
forward posture so the
anterior weak muscles would be
the neck flexors which are
inhibited and the posterior
weak muscles would be the
rhomboids and serratus
anterior okay so upper crossed
and also there is lower
crossed syndrome we'll focus
on the upper crossed syndrome
clinically for example
the work by vladimir janda
md and prague czech republic
there have been observed
patterns of muscle involvement
that have been called
upper and lower cross
syndromes. Upper because it
involves the upper body and
lower because it involves
the pelvis or lower body. It
is called crossed as there
are two lines that form
a crossover with anterior
muscles being facilitated
tight shortened type 1 muscles
and posteriorly follow
following one line call it
the facilitated or shortened
line with type 1 muscles
being also shortened
this is an in response to
a muscle imbalance
similarly follow the other
cross line that goes
from anterior posterior
representing the inhibited
and thus weak muscles
both anteriorly and
posteriorly so across syndromes
this is like a puzzle where
you have two lines with
four so-called stations two
anterior and two posterior
groups knowing the four
groups will give you an
understanding of which
muscles can be involved at any
one time so if the pectoralis
major is tight in front
you do have a cross syndrome
for example upper for
instance and you can deduce
which other muscles are
involved in a particular
patient here's another
schematic drawing for
you posture and the cross
syndromes again in this lecture
we'll focus on the upper
cross syndrome here circled
in blue so here in the
shaded light gray color
we have a line going from
front to back and I'm
going to go back one slide
so you can see this here
we go um here's the x
all right so this is the
crossed syndrome for the
upper crossed syndrome so
with the black lettering
here we're going to follow
this part of the x across
from front to back kind of
goes from higher to lower
but yes from front to
back and here we have the
inhibited neck flexors
so weak weak neck flexors
causing that head forward
position and then a follow
that line down to the
posterior side we have the
inhibited and thus weak
rhomboids and serratus anterior
we go to the other line
on this x or cross okay
anteriorly and posteriorly
in the pink letters and in
the front so this is the
tight now pectoralis and
then we follow the line
and over here again tight
tight on the whole line
front and back tight upper
trapezius and levator scapula
so this is all involved
the four stations and the
two lines making the cross
for the crossed syndrome,
upper crossed syndrome.
And we can see a listing
of more of the muscles
involved. Again, the
tight was the pink line
here. Here we have a listing
of the tight muscles.
On the left-hand side of this
image here, pec
major, pec minor,
upper trapezius, as
we noted here, levator
scapula, also
sternocleidomastoid and then
on this side to the
right of the picture
the weak muscles which we
had noted here on this line
with the the black letters
here okay so the lower and
the middle trapezius also
serratus anterior listed
again rhomboid major and
minor also those neck flexors
would be weak and that again
is this part of the cross
the x weak here weak weak
or inhibited and then again
this part of the cross or
the line okay all of these
muscles involved in being
tight okay so that's a review
and now we go to this slide
with the blue circles again
a review upper crust syndrome
is notated here here's
that same line with the
light gray box deep cervical
flexors are inhibited or weak
we follow it down inhibited
lower traps radius anterior
and the rest of the
muscles in the listing that
you saw in the previous slide
here in the white box for
the upper cross syndrome
here we have the other part
of the x or the cross okay
yes cross cross makes the
x so going on this diagonal
from front Up to back,
again, facilitated tight SCM
pectoralis and facilitated
upper trap levator scapula.
Okay, and so memorize
here anterior muscles
involved in the
upper crust syndrome.
So anterior postural
muscles, so getting tight.
Scalines, SCM, pec major,
upper pec minor. anterior
phasic muscles so getting
weak the deep cervical flexors
which you can kind of
see right over there in
that schematic drawing and
now posterior okay for the
upper cross syndrome
again memorizing posterior
muscles postural muscles
getting tight so this upper
trapezius levator scapula
cervical erector spinae
muscles posterior phasic
muscles thus getting weak
mid to lower trapezius,
rhomboids, latissimus dorsi.
So here's a clinical
association,
a patient with a head forward
posture and the
upper cross syndrome.
You can clearly see here to the
left, this is a
correct head posture.
Her external auditory
meatus is pretty much
in line with the
middle of her shoulder
joint versus here,
head forward posture.
So her plumb line
alignment is off.
She has an increased
thoracic kyphosis,
rounded shoulders, flexion
of the lower cervical
spine, an extension of
the upper cervical spine,
and muscle imbalance. So
tight, facilitated type 1
muscles versus the weak,
inhibited type 2 muscles.
The same muscles as
we had noted before.
Here's the clinical
correlation. You have this as an
assigned reading for this
lecture from Phil Page,
Cervicogenic Headaches and
Evidence-Led Approach to
Clinical Management. You
can click on this link here.
It's also noted in your
class preparation guide.
We note here, figures
2A and 2B. This
is from Yanda,
Dr. Yanda, that we
discussed his
cervical flexion test.
Letter A is normal. The
patient is able to lift
her head while lying supine
off the table. She has
the strength to do that,
the cervical flexion.
Letter B is showing an
abnormal movement pattern
in terms of her weak
anterior cervical flexors.
So figure A and B here
below, figure 6A and 6B,
this is a cranial
cervical flexion exercise.
against an elastic band
loop. So she's putting
both of her hands on the
inside of this TheraBand
loop and around the back
of her head. And the
exercise is for her to
push her head backwards.
Okay, you can see the
stretching of the band. And to
do that, she needs to use
the strength of the muscles
in the anterior part of
her neck. So trying to, if
there is weakness, this would
be an exercise to strengthen
that area. have. So take
a look at the rest of
the article. There's some
other clinical correlations
that you might find
interesting as well in terms of
the uppercross syndrome and
the overall patient care.
Okay, so besides
uppercross syndrome, we
can think of other
postural considerations,
and including postural
compensation and thinking about
that as an integrated
homeostatic process and in terms
of terminology we can think
of homeodynamics as well
so this begins in utero
and continues throughout
growth the central
nervous system and
peripheral nervous
system together learn to
balance the postural
homeostatic mechanisms.
So each person will
progressively compensate
in a different way
depending in part on his
or her unique intrinsic
and extrinsic risk
factors which we can
review in just a bit.
Postural preferences and
patterns will conform
within the resultant
connective tissue structure.
Neuromusculoskeletal
structures will remodel
to reflect the
functional demands placed
upon them, and functional
capability will
be limited by less
than ideal structure.
So other postural
considerations. Think of the
tensegrity model. Where
does this word come from?
Tensegrity. So originally
from an architect,
Buckminster Fuller in
1929. So two words,
tension plus integrity
equals tensegrity.
So T-E-N-S tensegrity,
tensegrity,
sometimes called biotensegrity.
This can also apply
to biological systems in
addition to architecture
the field of architecture
so in this tensegrity
model it is recognized
that areas of hypo meaning
little mobile mobility
hypo mobile somatic
dysfunction may cause
compensatory hyper a lot of
mobility hypermobility in
another region elsewhere.
And then vice versa.
Hypermobility in one or
more regions may affect
compensatory hypomobility
somewhere else.
So fascial patterning
and musculoligamentous
tensions take on
primary importance
as the model's
connecting elements.
We've often talked about this
in terms of other postural
considerations. Coronal
plane, looking for group
curves. Remember the type
1 group curves usually in
the thoracic lumbar region
could go up into the lower
cervical spine especially
if it's a full-fledged
scoliosis pattern that the
patient might have so keep that
in mind for the coronal
planes sagittal plane remember
the patient could have
increased kyphosis or
increased lordosis or lordoses
so keeping that in your
differential as you observe
the patient's posture there's
also the transverse plane
remember we had some labs
where we looked at
rotational preferences the
respiratory circulatory model
of gordon zinc do we looked
for zinc pattern references
in that horizontal plane
and there was common compensatory
patterns and uncommon
compensatory or uncompensated
patterns and there
were the importance of the
transitional regions at OA,
occipital atlantal, CT,
cervical thoracic, TL,
thoracolumbar and LS lumbosacral
regions was something that
we took a look at. And
since there's only four
regions and you were able to
do a pretty quick clinical
assessment, this is a nice
way to include an evaluation
in that area and see
what are the rotational
preferences, which may be
relating to the myofascial system
as well. And correlating
all of that, these
abnormalities or somatic
dysfunctions that you may find in
the coronal sagittal
transverse plane with somatic
dysfunctions that you find
as well okay moving on other
postural considerations we
can think about gravitational
strain pathophysiology
gsp signs and symptoms
can be changes or alterations
in postural alignment,
recurrent somatic dysfunctions,
lower back pain, referred
pain to the extremities,
headaches, somatovisceral
effects and presentations,
fatigue, and
weakness. And that can
progress to postural
decompensation. So they're no
longer just compensating,
they're becoming decompensated.
And that happens
when an individual's
functional homeostatic
mechanisms are overwhelmed, or
when the degree of
pathological change becomes
structurally incapable of
resisting gravitational force.
So we're always trying to
resist that force of gravity.
So other postural
considerations.
Again, we're sticking with
the gravitational strain
pathophysiology gsp
considerations there can
be intrinsic factors such
as a person's age do they
have muscle weakness do
they have how is their
fascial elasticity how is
the state of their bone
mass and other physical
characteristics two could
also be they have on
altered integrity or an
altered response from
their anti-gravity tissues.
Other intrinsic factors,
they may have incompetent
bony anti-gravity
structures, such as
maybe they have a spondylosis
or a spondylolisthesis.
They could also have
poor tissue health.
they could also have wedge
vertebra bony asymmetry
maybe in their sacrum or their
pelvis a shorter hemipelvis
they could have a state of
pregnancy or a state where
they are have increased
weight all of these intrinsic
factors may come into
play extrinsic factors now
could involve things such
as the patient had a history
of a motor vehicle accident
or they had a surgery
specifically maybe even a
laminectomy some kind of macro
trauma like that also sports
especially highly competitive
sports can be an extrinsic
factor gymnastics highly
competitive gymnastics
highly competitive sports,
weightlifting, football,
golf, all of these could lead
to micro traumas over time
as well. Those are some of
the extrinsic factors. In
terms of gravitational strain
pathophysiology and increased
gravitational forces
on a person, you could also
think of military pilots
who experience multiple g
-forces and the effect on their
body that's another extrinsic
factor that can affect
them we can also think about
tissue responses at all
of these different levels
okay so skeletal arthrodial
so the bones and the joints
we often talk about wolf
law, sometimes called wolf's
law, where bone remodels
over time in response to
the stresses placed upon it.
We can also talk about
regional or transitional zone
fascial responses that
came from J. Gordon Sintio
and the respiratory
circulatory model that you've
learned about recently and
the compensated and the
uncompensated preferences in
terms of that the zinc fascial
patterns in that respiratory
circulatory model
moving on from fascia bones
joints fascia to muscle we
have a muscular response
to the gravitational strain
pathophysiology which could
lead to trigger points
and these could be related
to myotomal so muscle
referred pattern or sclerotermal
kind of more ligamentous
pain patterns myotomal
sclerotermal pain patterns
and then tight versus weak
muscle patterns which is
what we're focusing on in
this lecture the upper crossed
and lower pelvic cross
syndromes here we're talking
more about the upper
cross syndrome and then a
ligamentous response is there
any ligamentous laxity and
are other approaches needed
for that type of treatment
and the response of the
related neural vascular
lymphatic and visceral elements
remember thinking about
the body as a whole not necessarily
just the musculoskeletal
we talked about muscular
response skeletal
response but also we there
is the nervous system the
vascular system we always
incorporate our understanding
of the lymphatic system and
the viscera very important
so thinking about the whole
picture on all the many
different levels okay so
continuing on with the
gravitational strain
pathophysiology considerations from
general diagnostic
considerations so the The purpose
of postural diagnosis,
therefore, is to determine where
in the continuum of a
given patient that they are
in terms of their posture
and whether the osteopathic
postural model, remember
we talked about the five,
maybe it's now six model
osteopathic models we have this
postural structural postural
structural or you could
call it biomechanical
postural biomechanical model
often just the biomechanical
model where the patient
is on that continuum but
remember this model postural
biomechanical is very much
related to the neurological
and autonomic model and as
we just discussed before
that respiratory circulatory
model. So there's crossover
and definite incorporation
within the five or six
models that we talked about
earlier in the lecture.
Okay,
so we want to know, should
this model, this postural
model, be integrated into
that patient's health care
program or regimen? To this
end, the diagnostic process
should answer at least
four specific questions.
Let's note, we note them
here. So does the patient's
posture play a role in the
patient's given complaint?
Something you need
to figure out.
Does the patient's
posture detract or limit
the patient's ability
for self-healing?
Consider that as well.
Does the patient's posture
present a significant
risk factor for pain,
dysfunction, or
pathology in the future?
And fourthly, is the
patient able to respond
positively to a postural
treatment regimen in a time
and cost effective manner
so helpful clinical
questions looking at the
whole picture for your
patient and what his his
her or their needs are okay
the postural diagnostic
approach to answering this
question relies heavily
on observation and
palpation, skills that you
have been working on for
the last year plus, okay?
So continuing on with
learning your observation
and palpation very well.
It attempts to correlate
other findings from the
patient's history and physical
examination in order to
determine if any pertinent
signs or symptoms exist. It may
also bring in radiological
or biomechanical tests to
help quantify the extent
or type of postural change.
So general strategies
for treatment.
We can first think about
postural education and
compliance. Secondly, osteopathic
manipulative treatment
provided generally and
to the transition zones.
Three, postural exercise.
Four, static postural
bracing when needed. Five,
functional postural
orthotics. And six,
other miscellaneous approaches.
And for more information,
you can always
click and this link
here will provide
more information in
some of these areas.
Okay, symptoms.
Compensatory or facilitative
mechanisms may cause
cervical, thoracic, lumbosacral
pain. You can see the
decompensations. Here's an
ideal plumb line posture
from a side view, parasagital
viewpoint, looking
from the right side. And we
can see some decompensation
here coming more forward
kind of slouching back
with an increased kyphosis
here increased lordosis
and kyphosis in this in this
picture so a forward pelvis
in this picture a little
bit of ptosis in the
abdomen in this picture in
this drawing and how these
compensations or
decompensations may cause
some gastrointestinal
disorders abdominal
pelvic inguinal pain,
headache and neck pain.
Okay, you can see how
these strains and pulls
look like they're
decompensating in a way that can
lead to somatic dysfunction
and or pain syndromes
for the patient. Okay, so
as a general wrap-up for
general treatment
strategies, overall there are
many many approaches that
are used to assist the
body's postural response to
gravity so an individually
designed conservative
program includes a carefully
selected combination
of patient education
osteopathic manipulative
treatment exercise and functional
orthotics when needed
all of these are aimed
at modifying the structure
function relationship,
sometimes called form
and function here,
and enhancing the body's
ability to self heal.
Therefore, postural
balancing requires an
understanding of the
biomechanical nature and
functional anatomy
of each patient and a
full understanding of
osteopathic philosophy.
so patients are also awakening
to the fact that current
conventional medical
interventions are often
dangerous costly and ineffective
the u.s medical system
continues to be the third
largest cause of death after
cardiovascular illness and
cancer to change this long
-term trend it is vital to
employ therapeutics that
are effective efficient and
relatively less expensive
and produce the least side
effects. The profession
needs to identify and
treat the root cause
of illness, be it of
the body, mind, spirit,
and or the energy fields
that support them.
The O's need to
develop, refine, and
use their osteopathic
skills so that they
can adhere to Dr.
Still's reminder.
To find health should be
the object of the doctor.
Anyone can find disease.
and to read more on this
topic feel free to click
on this link and it's
also noted in your cpg
and at the end of the end
of the lecture here in
the foundation's fifth
edition chapter 61 dynamic
strain and the bioenergetics
model for the last
part of this lecture we
will go over the upper
cross syndrome exercises.
First we will go over the upper
cross syndrome
stretching exercises.
Here is a stretch with a
picture for the scalenes.
Stabilizing the clavicle,
you can see the patient
holding there, tucking
their chin and side bending
the neck away from the
affected side for the
scalenes. Most of these for
the neck. These stretches
here, as noted in the
descriptions, are held for
about 15 to 20 seconds and
repeated on both sides.
Here for levator scapula,
for scalenes and levator
scapula, you can see
the patients holding the
edge of the treatment table
and then using their hand
on their shoulder for the
scalenes, hand on their
head turning away for
levator scapula. Here for
the SCM sitting at the
table supporting the back
of the head and using the
hand to allow a stretch
on the SCM.
Another stretch
for the upper cross
syndrome here the
patient is in the doorway
leaning forward with their
chest elbows at
about 90 degrees
so pec major pec
minor doorway stretch
and holding about
30 to 45 seconds.
And then a note here that
the patient could also
move their hands about
six inches higher as well
if they wanted to stretch
different muscle fibers.
Here's pec major, pec
minor, with more of a
stomach and chest
stretch, reaching all the
way up to the top if
they can reach, and then
leaning forward, pushing
out their stomach a
little bit, so you get
even a higher stretch.
okay upper cross syndrome
strengthening exercises we
have a few of those to go
over we saw this before
where the patient can do
some strengthening of the
cervical flexors and at the
same time it would lead to
stretching of the cervical
erector spinae on the posterior
side so they're lying
on their back there's a
thin towel or a thin a thin
pillow could be here and
it's as if their patient's
making a double chin and in
in this situation so it's
not actually the cervical
flexion test where they're
trying to lift their head
this is actually the
homework for strengthening so
they're just doing the
double chin tucking their
chin in they could do it
as a chin tuck so this time
instead of lying supine
they'll be standing and
then they tuck their chin
in again making that double
chin type of a motion
they mentioned here they
could do it with a tennis
ball under their chin as
well so it gives just another
physical clue or indicator
for the patient of what
the motion is that they're
doing for this one it's
for the trapezius mid
trapezius for the rhomboids
wrist to wall there are
patients standing against
the wall, arms out about,
straight out with the
elbows bent 90 degrees, and
then moving to the wall
and back with the wrists.
This one, patient's
lying prone, and
they have light
weight in their hands.
This is also mid
trapezius rhomboids.
Actually, this is prone,
and then they lift their
thumbs up towards the ceiling
in the last few degrees
and targets the rhomboids.
Here for latissimus dorsi
we have the patient up
against the wall reaching up
high and then they bring
their arms down to about
the level straight with their
fingers straight in line
with the shoulder level
okay and they have about a
90 degree angle between
their arm and their forearm
okay and doing several
repetitions of each of the
strengthening exercises okay
so as a summary the Uppercross
syndrome provides a clear
framework from which to
view a patient's postural
compensations and subsequently
target treatment approaches,
which can include an
exercise prescription, as
noted in the examples which
we just went over for
strengthening and stretching.
Other postural considerations
are manifold and
important to consider
in a patient's clinical
presentation. Application
of the osteopathic
perspective and the
osteopathic philosophy can be
beneficial for a patient's
overall well-being.
Here's the main
reference. We're sticking
with the fourth
edition, and the links
here are targeted for
your understanding.
The chapter 61 was added,
and feel free to take a
look at that one as well.
Chapter 92 has similar
content to the FOM4 assigned
reading. and then extra
reading here not required
and the page article
here is with the link noted
is also listed in your
cpg that one is required
as a clinical correlation
for you all right here's
the lecture and lab feedback
form thank you for your
time and I hope you
learned something in this
lecture thank you so much